Guide to the Prison Education Program Research Lab Oral Histories on Debt and Incarceration TAM.816
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Narrator 122, 2020; cuid36520 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_14)
  In this interview, Narrator 122 discusses how he had to budget, prioritize certain items at commissary buys, and would only purchase the cheap essentials that last a long time. He explains that incarcerated people have to rely on outside support systems, which often includes family members, because most of the food served at the mess hall is low quality and not enough to survive on. He recalls receiving food packages from his mother, which were meaningful to him because they are extremely expensive, time-consuming to put together, and strictly regulated by prisons. He also explains the importance of friendship inside prison in terms of sharing food items and splitting up tasks like cooking and cleaning. Narrator 122 describes how stamps and cigarettes function like currency in the informal economy and can be exchanged for snacks and other items. This interview sheds light on the necessity of outside support, the cost and bureaucracy that goes into receiving that support, and the purpose of the informal economy in filling gaps for people who do not have outside help.
- Narrator 123, 2020; cuid36521 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_15)
  At the time of this interview, Narrator 123 was in his late thirties, and living with his fiancee in New York City. He had recently returned home after serving over a decade in New York state prisons. Narrator 123 described himself as a fitness enthusiast, who loves spending his free time reading comic books and fantasy publications.
  In this interview, Narrator 123 talks about his jobs in mess halls, and how he operated an informal store of his own to make ends meet while he was incarcerated. He describes who purchased items from his store, how he expanded his inventory, and explains that running an informal store is one way that people like himself inside prison are able to secure enough food to eat. His account sheds light on the range of "hustles" within the prison informal economy.
- Narrator 124, 2020; cuid36522 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_16)
  Narrator 124 was released from prison in 2017, after serving an 11-year sentence in New York State. In his early thirties at the time of this interview, he lived in Queens, New York, working as a personal trainer and fitness instructor, an expertise that he developed while incarcerated.
  In this interview, Narrator 124 talks about the food items he purchased from the commissary store and what he purchased from the prison informal economy to save money. He recounts how selling magazines and Newports were his "hustles", which were necessary to supplement the money he received from his aunt and brother. His account sheds light on several features of the prison informal economy including the range of necessities sold like pots and pans, and what it is like to sell items within it.
- Narrator 127, 2020; cuid36523 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_17)
  Narrator 127, who was in his early 60s at the time of this conversation, was released in the Fall of 2018, after serving 9 years of an 11-year sentence in New York State prisons. When we interviewed him, Narrator 127 was living in the Bronx, spending most of his time as a caretaker for his elderly mother.
  In this interview, Narrator 127 talks about the prison informal economy and his state jobs in commissary stores and prison libraries, which together his livelihood depended on. He recalls that while he was working in the commissary store, he learned that the state makes a significant profit on sales. His account sheds light on the profits that prisons generate through price hikes on commissary items and wage stagnation.
- Narrator 130, 2020; cuid36524 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_18)
  Narrator 130 was in his mid-thirties at the time of the interview. He was released in the Spring of 2017, after spending over nine years in New York State prison. After his release, he moved to Florida where he found employment as a municipal worker for a local town.
  In this interview, Narrator 130 talks about the costs of eating, showering, and living in a prison cell. He describes the hygiene, food, and clothing items provided by the state and explains why they are insufficient. His account sheds light on the physical conditions inside prison including showers and cells, and the basic expenses that become the responsibility of incarcerated individuals or their loved ones.
- Narrator 132, 2020; cuid36525 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_19)
  Narrator 132 was born and raised in the eastern towns of Long Island, New York. Growing up, he was an outgoing, adventurous, and very curious kid. Narrator 132 was incarcerated for 13 years, and started his educational journey in his twelfth year in prison. At the time of the interview, he was pursuing his B.A. and working as a multimedia artist and visual storyteller.
  In this interview, Narrator 132 discusses how he had to survive on the bare minimum while he was incarcerated due to a lack of funds. He purchased necessities at the commissary store with the little money he made from his state job. He got by, by exchanging food he took from the mess hall for stamps or cigarettes, which functioned as forms of currency, or for other food items he needed. Narrator 132 also went to "stores" or "jugglers" and racked up a small amount of debt in order to buy snacks and other items. He explains that many other people inside were struggling like him and could not afford to max out at commissary. This interview sheds light on the function of jobs inside prison in facilitating exchanges through the informal economy, which allow incarcerated people to scrape by.
- Narrator 134, 2021; cuid36526 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_20)
  Narrator 134 was born and raised in New York City. He was released in the Spring of 2018, after serving 14 years in New York State prisons. At the time of this interview, Narrator 134 was in his mid-thirties, and lived in Queens, NY. He was studying to complete his B.A. degree, which he started while he was still incarcerated.
  In this interview, Narrator 134 explains that he did not struggle financially in prison thanks to support from his family members, friends, and girlfriends. They sent him packages with luxury items that were a mark of his status inside prison, as well as money for commissary. He describes the economic hierarchy inside prison, and how he would help out people in need, especially through his job as a porter and his gang membership. In addition, he leveraged his job as a porter to make extra money by selling illicit items within the prison and participated in the informal economy by gambling, reselling cigarettes, and selling drugs. This interview sheds light on how prisons are often segregated by status, social standing, ethnicity, and gang affiliation, as well as the ways specific jobs can facilitate trading through the informal economy.
- Narrator 223, 2020; cuid36527 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_21)
  Narrator 223, who was in her mid-fifties at the time of this interview, was born and raised in the Bronx, New York. When we spoke to her she was still living in the Bronx, and was working towards completing her college degree. Formerly incarcerated herself, Narrator 223 supported her son (Narrator 123) for over a decade during his own incarceration.
  In this interview, Narrator 223 talks about sending her son money and packages, and paying for phone calls while he was incarcerated. In addition, she explains why it was important for Narrator 123 and herself to financially support his daughter any way they could. However, it was not easy and she recalls finding a way to do so even when she was laid off from her job. Her account sheds light on the importance of showing incarcerated people that they are cared for and the financial hardship that families face.
- Narrator 232, 2020; cuid36528 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_22)
  Narrator 232 is a single parent living in Long Island, New York, where she spent most of her life. She is the second oldest of three siblings. She and her siblings were adopted as children and brought to New York from Puerto Rico.
  In this interview, Narrator 232 talks about her experience supporting her nephew, Narrator 132, who is like a son to her, during his incarceration and how she kept him motivated to continue his education inside prison. She describes how she used JPay to send him stamps and money for commissary, and her experience using the service to communicate with him. Her account sheds light on the expenses that households take on when a loved one is incarcerated, and the financial and emotional responsibilities so often shouldered by women.
- Narrator 325, 2021; cuid36529 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_23)
  Narrator 325, who was 69 years old at the time of this interview, was born in the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia but moved to the Bronx with his family as a child. Before being incarcerated, Narrator 325 served in the US Marine Corps. He returned to the Bronx in 2021, after serving 35 years in New York prisons. Now, he plans to open a non-profit to train service dogs to support disabled veterans, first responders, and the elderly.
  In this interview, Narrator 325 discusses JPay and the predatory, profit-driven nature of their services, and the few lackluster JPay benefits promised to incarcerated people during the pandemic. He recalls how JPay's promotional benefits often did not work, were temporary, and that the benefits were minimal themselves. Delays, design flaws, and product breakdowns were frequent but incarcerated people had little recourse. This interview sheds light on the profit motive behind JPay's services and how incarcerated people are often taken advantage of financially by such corporations.
- Narrator 326, 2021; cuid36530 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_24)
  Narrator 326 was in his mid-thirties at the time of this interview. Born in Brooklyn, New York, Narrator 326 lived in all the five boroughs, and in Westchester county. He returned to the Bronx in February 2021, after spending approximately 13 years in New York State prisons. When we met him, he was working as a porter cleaning buildings in the South Bronx and on construction sites. At the time, he said he was barely making ends meet and did not feel very optimistic that his financial situation would improve in the near future.
  In this interview, Narrator 326 discusses JPay and how the corporation took advantage of incarcerated people and their isolation during the pandemic. He recounts how the few promotional benefits they offered such as free stamps and messages encouraged more spending as incarcerated people had no other means of communicating with loved ones during lockdown. The lack of recreation, visitation, and mail all led to a dramatic increase in tablet usage for both communication and entertainment, thus increasing profits for JPay. This interview sheds light on the predatory, profit-driven nature of JPay's services and how incarcerated people are often taken advantage of financially by such corporations, particularly during a tumultuous time like the COVID-19 pandemic.
- Student Researchers Interview, 2021; cuid36531 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_25)
  Historical Note
  Zachary Gillespie is an undergraduate student in NYU's Department of Social and Cultural Analysis, majoring in American Studies. He has been a member of the NYU Prison Education Program Research Lab. Derick McCarthy is a student in the Department of Social and Cultural Analysis at NYU, majoring in American Studies. He is a member of NYU's Prison Education Program Research Lab. Mychal Pagan is an emerging multimedia artist studying at NYU's Gallatin School of Individualized Study. He is a member of NYU's Prison Education Program Research Lab, and he looks forward to a future in media and communications. Aiyuba Thomas is a graduate student at NYU's Gallatin School of Individualized Studies, and a member of NYU's Prison Education Program Research Lab. His research and professional work are centered around the social and financial redevelopment of disenfranchised and marginalized communities, including those who have been impacted by the justice system. Vincent Thompson recently graduated from the Department of Social and Cultural Analysis at NYU with a major in American Studies. A member of NYU's Prison Education Program Research Lab, he started Stopping the Cycle, a non-profit organization that helps individuals avoid incarceration.
  In the course of this group discussion, five members of NYU's Prison Education Program (PEP) reflect on their transition from prison inmates and students to their training as student researchers in the PEP Research Lab. They trade their experiences of life on the inside, debunking a variety of public myths about the welfare and treatment of those caught within the prison system. Discussing their post-carceral roles as students and researchers, they analyze the differences between the two, drawing particular attention to the social status accorded to researchers. Building on the independence and resources offered by PEP's Research Lab, they describe the initiatives they have taken to launch new paths of inquiry into carceral life and the financial and social burdens that continue to afflict formerly incarcerated on reentry.